NICOLÁS URDANETA

n.urdaneta@duke.edu nicolasurdaneta.github.io (+1) 217-9795876

Last updated: July 2023

Profile

I am an economics PhD student at Duke University. I previously worked as research assistant at the Economics Faculty at Universidad de Los Andes, Colombia, working for Marcela Eslava on firm dynamics, productivity, and market power. I hold a M.A and a B.A. in economics from Universidad de Los Andes. I am primarily interested in approaching problems through empirical work with structural models. My current research interests are in firm dynamics, innovation, trade, market power, economic development, and applied econometrics. I also work on other projects on internal migration and displacement in Colombia and gender bias in student evaluations of teaching.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Economics, Duke Univeristy .	2022 - Present
M.A. Economics, Universidad de los Andes - Colombia (cum laude).	2019 - 2021
B.A. Economics, Universidad de los Andes - Colombia (cum laude).	2015 - 2019

Published papers

The Size and Life-Cycle Growth of Plants: The Role of Productivity, Demand, and Wedges. (2023). The Review of Economic Studies. With Marcela Eslava and John Haltiwanger. Document available here.

Working Papers

Market Concentration, Market Fragmentation, and Inequality in Latin America. (2021). UNDP LAC Working Paper No. 11. Background Paper for the UNDP LAC Regional Human Development Report 2021. With *Marcela Eslava* and *Marcela Meléndez*. Working paper available here.

"Talented" Men and "Kind" Women? Gender Bias in Student Evaluations of Teaching. (2021). Documento CEDE No. 46. (Master's thesis). Document available here. In the media: El Espectador.

Work in progress

Equilibrium Gender Discrimination in Student Evaluation of Teaching. With Sara Ayllon, Lars Lefgren, Richard Patterson, and Olga Stoddard.

Reconciling the Effects of Migration: Do the Opportunity Costs Shape the Local Effects?. With Mateo Arbeláez and Juan Sebastián Muñoz.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant for Marcela Eslava, Full-Professor and Economics Dean, Universidad de Los Andes. Main research projects joint with John Haltiwanger and Marcela Meléndez (Jun. 2019 - Jul. 2022).

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Impact Evaluation for Public Policy (prof. Adriana Camacho)	2020 II
Intermediate Econometrics (prof. Mateo Arbeláez)	2020 Summer
World Economic History (prof. Leopoldo Fergusson and Juan Sebastián Galán)	2020 I
Intermediate Macroeconomics (prof. David Pérez and Andrés Zambrano)	2019 II & 2020 I

Undergraduate Teacher Assistant - Universidad de Los Andes

Monetary Policy and Theory	2018 II & 2019 I
Intermediate Econometrics	2018 Summer
Intermediate Microeconomics	2017 Summer
Mathematical Methods for Economics	2017 II
Study hall for Calculus 3, Integral Calculus, Linear Algebra, and Diffe	erential Calculus. 2017 I
Integral Calculus	2016 II

AWARDS

Sixth place National Colombian Mathematical Olympics 30th Edition. First level category.	2011
Noche de los mejores. One of the best results in the Colombian higher education examinations	
(Saber-Pro). The award was given to 1,324 graduates out of over 240,000.	2019

OTHER EXPERIENCE

Supuestos Economics Magazine (2016 - 2019). This is the economics student's magazine from Universidad de Los Andes. I held multiple roles: Editorial Director (2019), Revision and Edition Sub Director (2018), Communications Sub Director (2017 II). Six publications in printed edition, including two main articles. Link to website (in Spanish).

SKILLS

Lars Lefgren

DIVILLO				
Stata, R & Latex	Advanced	Python & Julia	Basic	
LANGUAGES				
English	Fluent	Spanish	Native Language	
REFERENCES				
Marcela Eslava	Full Professor and Econ meslava@uniandes.edu.co	nomics Dean, Unive	ersidad de Los Andes.	
John Haltiwanger	Distinguished University Professor, University of Maryland. halt@umd.edu			
Adriana Camacho	Associate Professor, Universidad de Los Andes. adcamach@uniandes.edu.co			

and

Professor,

Bringham

Young

University.

Department Chair lars_lefgren@byu.edu